Guide to the George Crabbe Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Crabbe collection
1776-1932
GEN MSS 230
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.4
(2 boxes)
Comprised of letters from Crabbe to various people, including Bernard Barton, Edmund Burke, George Crabbe (his son), Thomas Crofton Croker, and Alethea Lewis (concerning Crabbe's fiancee, Sarah Elmy); manuscripts of two poems ("Belinda Waters" and "Note Our Manor Lord..."); a manuscript notebook of poems; notes for a sermon; a fragment of a printed form ordering the removal of William Merchant from the Parish of Trowbridge to the Parish of East Knoyle (signed by Crabbe); and a scrapbook (1819-1932) of material about Crabbe, including engravings and clippings.
Crabbe, George, 1754-1832
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials acquired from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to George Crabbe.
Poetry; Belinda Waters; Barton, Bernard, 1784-1849; Burke, Edmund, 1729-1797; Crabbe, George, 1754-1832; Crabbe, George, 1785-1857; Croker, Thomas Crofton, 1798-1854; Lewis, Alethea, 1749-1827
- Letters from George Crabbe (1754-1832), 1819 Aug 10
  - ALS to Bernard Barton, Trowbridge, 1819 Aug 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ALS to Edmund Burke, Bishopsgate Street [London], 1781 Jun 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    This letter was given by Mr. Burke to Sir Charles Bunbury, another patron of Mr. Crabbe's, and was printed in The Correspondence of Sir Thomas Hanmer, edited by Sir Henry Bunbury, London, 1838. Tinker 763
  - ALS to Edmund Cartwright, Muston, 1789 Oct 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Accompanied by a photograph of Crabbe.
  - ALS to Miss Charter, Trowbridge, 1815 Jul 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Published in Broadley & Jerrold, The Romance of an Elderly Poet..., London, 1913, p. 91-96.
  - 4 ALS to his son, George Crabbe, Bath and Trowbridge, 1824 Mar 6-1830 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AL to George Crabbe (his son), Trowbridge, n.d. [after 1820] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Signature clipped out. Concerning a misunderstanding between the elder Crabbe and his grand-daughter.
  - ALS to Thomas Crofton Croker, Trowbridge, 1827 Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - ALS to James Donn, Grantham, 1813 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AL to Sir George Smith Gibbes, No. 4 Gay Street [London], 1825 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Concerning a letter from Prince Hoare.
  - 2 ALS to Dr. Gordon, the Dean of Lincoln, Muston and [n.p.], 1814 Apr 5, [n.y.] Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - ALS to [Dr. Gordon], the Dean of Lincoln, Trowbridge, 1814 Jul 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Tinker 779
  - ALS to [Althea Lewis], 1776 Feb 24 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ALS to E. Magrath, Trowbridge, 1827 Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - ALS to Samuel Jackson Pratt, Grantham, 1810 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ALS to John Robinson, Glemham, 1798 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Enclosure for Mr. Pugh wanting in letter.
  - Letter by an amanuensis to John Robinson, Glemham, 1798 Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - ALS to [Samuel Rogers], [Newbridge?], [1816?] Jul 2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - ALS to Sarah Rogers, London, [1816] Jun 12 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - ALS to [the Secretary of the Royal Society of Literature], Trowbridge, 1825 Apr 11 (Box 1, Folder 18a)
    Tinker 765
  - ALS to John Waldron, Jr., Trowbridge, [n.y.] Jan 22 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - ALS to Miss Waldron, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - ALS to Alaric A. Watts, Trowbridge, 1826 Sep 27 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Tinker 783
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient, London, [1817?] (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Paper is watermarked 1811.
- Letter to George Crabbe (1754-1832), 1809 Oct 21
  - Scott, Sir Walter (1771-1832). ALS (facsimile), Abbotsford, 1809 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 22a)
- Letters from George Crabbe (1785-1857), 1851 May 15
  - ALS to an unidentified correspondent, Bredfield, 1851 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Autograph (clipped from letter), [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Letters to George Crabbe (1785-1857), 1838 Jun 27, 1839 Feb 11
  - Crombie, Alexander. 2 ALS, London, 1838 Jun 27, 1839 Feb 11 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Crowfoot, William Henchman. ALS, 1845 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Davidson, G. W. ALS, 1835 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - King, William. ALS, Brighton, 1847 Jul 2 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Empty folder (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Writings and Documents of George Crabbe (1754-1832)
  - Belinda Waters (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Autograph manuscript of a portion of the poem beginning "She had Clarrisa for her hearts dear friend ..." On second leaf: 23 lines of an unidentified poem beginning "Note our Manor Lord, no part hath he ..." Tinker 761
  - Notebook, Sidmouth and Trowbridge, 1816 Sep-Oct (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Autograph manuscript notebook of eight leaves containing poetry in ink and pencil.
  - Notes for a sermon on Psalm 9, ver. 17, 1789-1820 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Part of a printed form ordering the removal of William Merchant from the Parish of Trowbridge to the Parish of East Knoyle, 1831 Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    The form is filled out in manuscript, possibly in the hand of George Crabbe. Signed by George Crabbe and W. E. Waldron. On the verso is a note in the hand of Crabbe suspending the order on account of the illness of William Merchant, signed by Waldron and Crabbe. Endorsed: Suspending Order for Wm. Merchant.
  - School-Day Friendship (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Autograph manuscript signed by George Crabbe, of the first three stanzas of his poem, with slight variations from the printed text. Beneath the signature is a note "Extract from an unpublished poem. -1831." First published with the title "The School Fellow" in Posthumous Poems of the Rev. George Crabbe edited by his son, Philadelphia, 1835, p. 127. Tinker 762
  - Scrapbook of material about Crabbe, 1819-1932 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Volume labeled "Autograph Letters of George Crabbe", n.d.
    Contains portraits of Crabbe; letters were removed.
- Oversize, n.d.
  - Volume labeled "Autograph Letters of George Crabbe", n.d. (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 36)